Ivan Pestunov

Product Manager +7 965 277 63 12, <u>ipestunov@gmail.com</u>, Telegram @ipestunov, <u>LinkedIn</u>

PROFILE

Product Manager with 6+ years of experience.

12 years of overall experience in software development (web, backend, databases, iOS, Android, SQL, reports) in the leadership, product and technical roles.

Working with remote teams since 2011.

EXPERIENCE

Product Lead, International Express Delivery, X5 Retail Group, Moscow, Russia — 2021–Current X5 Retail Group is the largest retail company in Russia, combining several largest chains of proximity markets and supermarkets along with the portfolio of digital services, offering express and scheduled groceries delivery, loyalty programs and food-focused media.

- Coordinated the efforts of multiple distributed teams (60+ contributors; teams including frontend, backend, iOS, Android, DWH, DevOps, IT support, translation, business and system analysis) to implement the launch of a new e-com platform (express groceries delivery) in Latin America.
- Contributed to the growth and organization of the independent team (25+ contributors) dedicated to the product.
- Established the development pipeline and roadmap for subsequent product development (incl. new design, new payment integrations and delivery modes).
- Coordinated communication with international English speaking technical and business teams.
- The product experienced stable 20% M-t-M growth in 2022.

International Development Lead, MyBook.ru, LitRes, Moscow, Russia — 2019-2021

LitRes is the leading ebook and audiobook online retailer in Russia. <u>MyBook.ru</u> is the leading ebook and audiobook subscription service in Russia, belonging to the portfolio of LitRes projects, with iOS and Android apps consistently in the Top 5 in the Books Category of the Russian App Store and featured by the App Store team multiple times.

- Led a small team (1 product manager, 2 backend developers, 1 QA), dedicated to the international effort.
- Led the effort to implement localisation and internationalisation engine, launched a new product offering and business model in Estonia.
- Led the effort to develop Family Subscription plan and Logged-In Device Management for Estonian and Russian offerings.
- After completing Integrators Training by Adizes Institute, served for 1.5 years in a parallel role as a facilitator for the Organizational Change processes (contributing to significant changes as quarterly planning improvements, formation of dedicated cross-functional agile teams, company-wide performance review improvements, COVID-19 remote work and back to office transition).

Product Manager, Zvukislov.ru, LitRes, Moscow, Russia — 2016-2019

- Led a small team (1 product manager, 1 backend developer, 1 frontend developer, 1 QA), dedicated to the development of the audiobook subscription service.
- Led multiple product launches (Android app, website, iOS app redesign, podcasts catalogue), contributing to customer base and revenue growth.
- Managed collaboration with in-house and contractor teams (iOS, Android, backend).

- Led Carplay support implementation on iOS.
- Coordinated marketing efforts (discounts, activation and acquisition campaigns, email campaigns) to grow customer base.
- Implemented SQL reports and dashboard to measure daily product performance.
- Participated in hiring product managers, QA engineers.

QA Engineer, MyBook.ru, LitRes, Moscow, Russia — 2012-2016

- Performed full scale quality assurance processes (system analysis, functional, regression testing) for public launch of MyBook.ru website.
- Performed QA activities and developer contractor management during the launch of 1.0 versions of iOS and Android apps.
- Performed system analysis and QA in integration projects (payment providers, iOS and Android billing systems, marketing partnerships, analytics systems Google Analytics, Appsflyer, Amplitude, Yandex.Metrica).
- Routine QA for all current development tasks (frontend, backend, reporting, integration, iOS, Android).

Project lead, AT Consulting, Moscow, Russia -2011-2012

AT-Consulting provides digital consulting, integration, Data WareHouse and Business Intelligence services for leading companies in Russia, including telecommunications and banking clients.

- Led a 2-people team (1 backend developer, 1 frontend developer), developing the in-house system for automated testing on BI and DWH projects.
- Managed backlog, requirements, task definition and sprints.
- Implemented the system on 5 business projects and led in-house training for analysts on using the system.

QA Engineer, AT Consulting, Moscow, Russia — 2010-2011

- Performed quality assurance (manual, regression, automated testing) on DWH projects for telecommunication clients.
- Participated in the rollout of Agile methodology, helping to implement Scrum teams and sprints.

EDUCATION

Moscow Aviation Institute, Moscow, Russia — Applied Mathematics Engineer, 2011

SKILLS

- Product discovery: gather hypotheses, ICE/RICE scoring, prioritization.
- Create roadmaps, analyse scope, stages, dependencies and timelines, align with the involved teams and business stakeholders.
- Prepare business requirements and tech specs for epics and features.
- System analysis: create principal schemes, architecture, scenarios and state flows for frontend, backend, API systems.
- UI analysis and design: create scenarios, state flows and mockups for UI.
- Participate in the solution and system design stages with the technical leads to suggest possible architecture approaches and ensure all use cases and flows will get included in the implemented solution.
- Manage backlog, requirements, epics, task definitions and sprint content in JIRA or other systems.
- Maintain the specs during development, serving as a central point for answering questions and resolving uncertainties.
- Participate as a Product Owner in product testing activities, UAT, review and rollout in production.

- Create and maintain product documentation for stakeholders, developers, cross-functional peers, users, customer support.
- Run agile meetings: backlog refinement, backlog grooming, task estimation, sprint planning, daily stand-ups and retrospectives.
- Facilitate group meetings: brainstorming, problem solving, status reports.
- People management (hiring, 1:1, performance reviews).
- Create and analyse product reports (conversion funnels, cohorts, daily activity, retention).
- Setting up and using 3rd party analytics systems (Google Analytics, Appsflyer, Amplitude, Firebase).
- PM tools (JIRA, Confluence, Google Docs, Miro, Figma, roadmaps, Gantt charts).
- Strong quality assurance sills.
- Fluent SQL skills.

PERSONAL INFO

Languages: Russian (native), English (fluent).

Technical background (QA, software development, engineering education).

Interested in personal productivity (Getting Things Done, Zettelkasten style note taking, Tools for thought).